Guide to the NYU Abu Dhabi Memory Project Collection AD.RG.023
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
- Interviews with NYUAD Community Members [post-Covid], Fall 2022 - Present
  - Interview session with Nouf Al Hamly, Rawdha Rashed Almansoori and Lauren Kata (Citizen Researcher) (01:46:38), 9 December 2022; ADRG023_088 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_088)
    In this interview, Nouf and Rawdha discuss the evolving culture at NYUAD. Nouf describes the Downtown Campus as having a "start-up" feel, linking the shift to the Saadiyat campus with governmental changes. Rawdha highlights the importance of interdepartmental collaboration at Saadiyat. Nouf also details her department's efforts to engage the local community with university research and to reframe research from a Western perspective to include Emirati knowledge and practices. The discussion then moves to the Citizen Researcher program, covering its interdisciplinary nature, the vital role of students, its outreach to underfunded schools, the researcher lifecycle, COVID-19's impact, and examples from the Digital Humanities showcasing its breadth beyond STEM.
  - Interview session with Bonnie Sutherland (Library) and Lauren Kata (01:48:41), 09 December 2022; ADRG023_089 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_089)
    Video-recorded session with Bonnie Sutherland, Library Assistant in Acquisitions, recorded on 09/12/2022, and facilitated by Lauren Kata NYUAD University Archivist. Conducted as part of The Memory Project. The Memory Project is the NYUAD Library's contribution to celebrating the memories, experiences, traditions, stories and community history of NYU Abu Dhabi. Interviews will be preserved as part of the NYUAD University Archives.
    Keywords:
    Jamaica Khalifa City Emirates/Etihad Khalifa B School American International School Library Acquisitions DTC Expat culture
    Segments:
    Talking about the community of Jamaicans in the UAE, specifically about how important it is to feel at home abroad. Also a mention to how Bonnie and her family pioneered this community, paving the path for over 50 Jamaican families to emigrate in a similar way @ 22:55 - 28:35
    First impressions of the UAE @ 47:00 - 49:00
    Impressions and the role of the library at the beginning, at DTC. Also some mentions of the beginning of acquisitions at NYUAD in DTC @ 49:10 - 54:00
    Very interesting, early practices at the Library such as how everyone had a desk shift no matter what their role was and how there was weekly time set out to talk about yourself and your job to the rest of the Library team @ 59:00 - 1:00:00
    DTC - Saadiyat Move @ 1:15:00 - 1:20:00
    Difference between bookstore and library acquisitions @ 1:20:00 - 1:24:00
    Leisure Collection @ 1:24:00 - 1:26:00
  - Interview Session with Mayada Oudah (Campus Cats) and Lauren Kata (01:22:59), 06 November 2023; ADRG023_090 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_090)
    Video-recorded session with Mayada Oudah - Medisearch Associate at Social Science Experimental Lab, recorded on 2023-11–6 and facilitated by Lauren Kata - Assistant Academic Librarian for Archives and Special Collections. Conducted as part of The Memory Project. The Memory Project is the NYUAD Library's contribution to celebrating the memories, experiences, traditions, stories and community history of NYU Abu Dhabi. Interviews will be preserved as part of the NYUAD University Archives.
    Mayada Oudah shares her academic journey from computer science to interdisciplinary research in human-robot interaction at a UAE lab. Reflecting on the region's rapid AI growth, she discusses her diverse interests, from biometric technology integration to virtual reality experiments. Beyond her academic and research pursuits, she passionately narrates her involvement in managing campus cat populations both at her previous university and at NYUAD. She describes her approach of the Trap-Neuter-Return program, underscoring her commitment to animal welfare and community perspectives. Mayada shares her insights into the values and challenges of maintaining a campus cat colony, and spotlights some of the more well-known cats of the campus.
    Beginning of Cat Care Journey: Mayada describes the start of her journey in caring for campus cats, expressing her initial concerns and how she became an activist. (00:22:05 - 00:23:01)
    Discovering Campus Cat Protocols: Mayada recalls the moment she discovered protocols in place for managing the cat population on campus and her subsequent decision to reach out for support. (00:23:25 - 00:24:00)
    Challenges Faced During Covid: Mayada discusses the challenges faced in maintaining the campus cat community, particularly during the COVID-19 pandemic. (00:34:20 - 00:34:39)
    Personal Value of Cats: Towards the end, Mayada reflects on the value of cats in her family, viewing them as essential and beloved members. (00:35:30 - 00:35:44)
  - Interview session with Githmi Rabel, Huma Umar, Sidra Dahhan, and Stefan Mitikj (The Gazelle) and Lauren Kata (01:42:16), 21 May 2023 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_091)
    Githmi Rabel, Huma Umar, Sidra Dahhan, and Stefan Mitikj form the editorial management team of the Gazelle for AY22-23. In this interview, they discuss their individual journeys and experiences with the University's independent weekly student publication and reflect on their initial involvement, sharing personal anecdotes about joining as writers and later taking on editorial roles. The team members highlight the importance of the Gazelle in providing a platform for diverse voices within the unique context of NYU Abu Dhabi and the broader Middle East. They discuss the publication's role in offering nuanced perspectives on local and global issues, shedding light on topics that might be overlooked by mainstream media. Additionally, they delve into the challenges they face, emphasizing the importance of maintaining editorial independence while navigating complex cultural and institutional landscapes. The team expresses their commitment to upholding the Gazelle's responsibility to hold institutions accountable and their dedication to providing valuable insights into the Global South through their reporting.
  - Interview session with (Al Diwan SIG) Mohammed Muqbel, Roudha Almarzouqui, Aisha Alhammadi, Fatima Al Breiki, Mohammad Amjed, Shamma AlMansoori and Lauren Kata (01:50:35), 10 July 2023 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_092)
    In this interview, leaders of Al Diwan, student interest group dedicated to Arabic poetry and literature, discuss the significance of their group on a university campus. They emphasize the importance of Arabic poetry in understanding and preserving cultural identity, highlighting the unique linguistic and cultural nuances that distinguish it from other forms of poetry. The members express a commitment to fostering a sense of community and inclusivity, mentioning plans to expand the scope of their activities to include Arabic literature beyond just poetry. They acknowledge the challenges associated with proficiency in the Arabic language but stress that curiosity and passion are more critical criteria for joining their organization. Additionally, the interview touches upon the creative aspect of the organization, with plans for workshops to encourage students to write their own Arabic poetry.
  - Interview session with Peter Christensen (CABO) and Lauren Kata (01:52:16), 19 Dec 2023 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_093)
    In this interview, Peter L. Christensen highlights the significance of aligning resources with the academic mission and contrasts NYU Abu Dhabi's governance structure with other organizations. He delves into the complexity of the governance process, emphasizing the annual negotiations and budget examinations between NYU and Tamkeen. Reflecting on the institution's evolution, Christensen acknowledges its transition from a more informal environment to a mature and professional institution. He expresses gratitude for the significant financial support NYU Abu Dhabi receives from Tamkeen and the positive spirit and constant focus on possibilities within the institution. Overall, the discussion provides insights into the governance, resource management, and evolution of NYU Abu Dhabi, as well as the appreciation for the support received from stakeholders.
  - Interview session with (Core Technology Platform Scientists) James Weston, Matthew O'Connor, Rachid Rezgui and Lauren Kata, 19 Jan 2024 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_094)
    In this interview session, James Weston, Rachid Rezgui, Matthew O'Connor reflect on their experiences in laboratory management and the transition between different campus facilities, as Research Instrumentation Scientists of the Core Technology Platform operation at NYUAD. They share anecdotes about their professional journeys, including challenges faced during lab retrofits and office space transitions. The conversation highlights the evolution of laboratory infrastructure and the importance of adapting to changing environments. The group also discusses the complexities of moving equipment and navigating logistical challenges during the facility and campus relocation to Saadiyat Island in 2014. Throughout the discussion, there is a strong emphasis on the collaborative spirit and commitment to excellence that characterizes their work at NYU Abu Dhabi.
  - Interview session with Diana Chester (early NYUAD) and Lauren Kata, 07 May 2024 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_095)
  - Interview session with Saba Brelvi (Domestic Workers) and Lauren Kata, 23 May 2024 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_096)
  - Interview session with Sana Odeh (NYUAD Hackathon) and Lauren Kata, 11 June 2024 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_099)
  - Interview session with Joseph "Yosi" Gelfand (Physics Program) and Lauren Kata, 24 June 2024 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_100)
  - Interview session with Danny Abbas (IT) and Lauren Kata, 20 Sept 2024 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_101)
  - Interview session with Nevzat Ertunga "Ertu" Sarisozen (NYUAD Alumni Reunion) and Lauren Kata, 22 Nov 2024 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_102)
  - Interview session with Adam Fejes (NYUAD Alumni Reunion) and Lauren Kata, 22 Nov 2024 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_103)
  - Interview session with Otari Kakhidze (NYUAD Alumni Reunion), 23 Nov 2024 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_104)
  - Interview session with Staff Council AY24-25 and Lauren Kata, 22 April 2025 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_105)
  - Interview session with Andrea Maccio (Astrophysics and Space Science Ctr) and Lauren Kata, 10 June 2025 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_106)
  - Interview session with Anthony Tzes (Artificial Intelligence and Robotics Ctr) and Lauren Kata, 17 June 2025 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_107)
  - Interview session with Tracy Lavin (15-Year Club/Community Engagement) and Lauren Kata, 18 June 2025 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_108)
  - Interview session with Clodagh Girvan (15 Year Club), 20 June 2025 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_109)
  - Interview session with Nikos Nikiforakis (Behavioral Instructional Design Ctr) and Lauren Kata, 22 July 2025 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_110)
  - Interview session with Nancy Gleason (Hilary Ballon Ctr for Teaching and Learning) and Lauren Kata, 22 July 2025 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_111)
  - Interview session with Pance Naumov (Smart Engineering Materials Ctr) and Lauren Kata, 25 July 2025 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_112)
    Includes a Part 1 and a Part 2 -- Part 1 mostly includes Pance describing his background and the Center; Part 2 inludes further interview questions.
  - Interview session with Azza Abouzied (Ctr for Interacting Urban Networks - CITIES) and Lauren Kata, 30 July 2025 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_113)
  - Interview session with Julie Thurston (Facilities and Planning) and Lauren Kata, 04 Sept 2025 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_114)
  - Interview session with Tala Hammash (Community Outreach/Admissions) and Lauren Kata, 10 Oct 2025 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_115)
  - Interview session with John Burt (MUBADALA ACCESS Ctr) and Lauren Kata, 30 Oct 2025 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_116)
  - Interview session with Abdullah Alhussni and Guli Habibullaeva (Muslim Students Association SIG) and Lauren Kata, 04 Dec 2025 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_117)
  - Interview session with Ayesha Ahmed (NYUAD Alumni Reunion) and Lauren Kata, 14 Nov 2025 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_118)
  - Interview session with Ahmed Meshref (NYUAD Alumni Reunion) and Lauren Kata, 14 Nov 2025 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_119)
  - Interview session with Salwa Mikdadi (Al Mawrid Ctr) and Lauren Kata, 22 Jan 2026 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_120)
  - Interview session with Anne-Lise Tropato (Falcon Heritage) and Lauren Kata, 23 Jan 2026 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_121)
  - Interview session with Monica Menendez (Ctr for Interacting Urban Networks: CITIES) and Lauren Kata, 27 Jan 2026 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_122)
- Citizen Archivist Memory Recordings [IN PROCESS]
  The Citizen Archivist series of the NYUAD Memory Project includes short, audio-recorded interview sessions with both members of the NYUAD Community and members of the external community who visited campus during one of the University's "Open Campus Day" opportunities. "Become a Citizen Archivist" is an open, walk-in session that has been offered during several iterations of Open Campus Day.